well welcome to our control room
um we're about two flights up in our
auditorium
uh directly above the doors when you
enter so can i give you a rundown
um we actually had a really cool
opportunity to really start from scratch
in the space
because there wasn't a whole lot of tlc
from the beginning here
about two years ago we had um no glass
in here
uh actually about a year ago actually we
had no glass there was no carpet it was
a
that cheap kind of um vinyl flooring
which is fine for like a home but when
you have a high traffic area
it didn't last at all and we had a
particle board desk that
was flexing um and so and then cables
just
kind of everywhere so really cool
opportunity to do it right
and i'll show you some of the things we
were intentional about but
we're breaking down the station so over
here we have lighting land
uh we are running jans vista and with
everything we try to be good stewards
so um this computer is actually probably
about seven years old i think
and it used to be our graphics computer
and then it got demoted to lighting
so if it works we use it um so
we're using vista for our lighting
software with the 1m the
usb jams now it's a chroma qvista uh if
you're doing lighting
from today i would not do this this is
about a thousand dollars for this plus
for the software plus the computer i
would use light key it's
an amazing mac tool it's like 90 bucks
works great but this was already
in the works um before i came on board
so i'm not that
time to just really was the best option
in terms of budget so
but if you're once you're doing anything
crazy um light could be the way to go
moving on we have graphics we recently
upgraded appropriate r7 to make things
so much simpler um we used to use pro 6
and we actually had to have not one not
two
but three computers to run our graphics
and the reason for that was
we had these three screens using a
triple head to go that was one machine
we had pastors tv and back wall that was
another machine and then we had a lower
thirds for broadcast that was another
machine
and pro 6's are limited so we upgraded
the pro seven
um and then we got this guy here which
has five
uh outputs and then we have this alpha
keyer which does our lower thirds and
all it does
it gets random right from purple center
right there so
this guy down here probably looks really
cool these are just this is a control
surface
to talk to our video matrix if you don't
know what a video matrix is
think of like the av receiver you might
have at your home
where you have a bunch of hdmi ins and
you know maybe an output to your tv
except
rather than it being hdmi it's sdi and
rather being one output
it's 40 inputs and 40 outputs so every
projector
every computer out input every camera
input everything
goes in the matrix and lets us route
things so if you notice on sunday when
steve's tv
is black it's actually not off it just
we're just sending a black signal
as one of our inputs we have a black
signal and if i want to route
uh the probe center signal to it just
click this button and then
take it and then now his tv would appear
to turn on it was on the whole time it
just
had a black signal up so i can now do
that
and that's we can program this to do
anything uh moving on we have a phone
uh this is useful for talking to
downstairs we can also call our student
room if we have a multi-room event going
on
and this also acts as a com system of
sort so
if i click audio
you might not be able to hear there's a
phone ringing in our audio room over
there
and that's how we can talk to each other
so as a video director or as the
graphics director i can pick up and call
them
and they can call me and then also we
have one at front of house so we can
ring in front of house
it does not actually ring the phone it
just flashes the light though since
they're in service
this is a much cheaper system since we
already had a phone system versus
installing something like clearcom
um so that that's a good solution
security radio for
talking to our our sheriff's office
officer we have on site
and then here is video world so this is
where we mix video from
um this is just a control surface though
actually there's only one cable plugged
into this thing and it's this guy it's a
poe cable
it's all powered over the network um
i'll plug that back in
and so um
this guy is how we uh switch cameras so
um before while this turning back on i
probably shouldn't have unplugged that
i'll explain what's happening up here so
this monitor right here
is our multi-view monitor we have
preview program
meters there it's just as the director i
like to see make sure we have audio
flowing
cameras one two three four five as well
as stage display so actually i
open up pro presenter here
[Music]
let it spin
i tried to run this on a mac mini even
the new ones and it would not work we
had to use an imac
um but i'll go ahead and just fire up
uh one of the slides here
sweet okay cool so now you can see i
have graphics coming in that's just
the left screen so we can that that
little is a copy of that and that's how
we can take a graphic and put it on
broadcast
and then right here i have words and i
also have the clock there
if a video rolls i get a blue clock and
that's super helpful because
as a video director i can see how much
time is left obviously we're never
perfect with the clock
but we try to be um and i have no idea
what music is playing right now
but if i roll a video so i'll just roll
this is announcements you see i can
you see i have actually a timer there
which is really nice
let me get that off all right so uh
that way i can i can select the camera
so i'll choose camera one
and if i want to take that camera i can
either use the t-bar to take the camera
which is this guy here
i can use the cut button um and then i
can also uh
use the transition button i can do
titles so
um we actually have media players built
in to the switcher so i can media
players
i can go to media player four i think
yeah so force and then i can do
i'll switch it back to that if i hit
this button here i have a keyer built in
i can just boop
title away and i actually have more than
once if i leave this on
i can spin this knob here and you'll see
as i spin the knob
it changes so yeah there's graphics so
we use that a lot the second one here or
the first one rather is actually for our
lyrics
so if i go to pro presenter and i hit a
lyric
this guy sends that to the switcher and
you can see i have that which would
normally be on the left and right screen
and then i have my lyrics there
and if whatever reason if i need to turn
that off i can just hit this button
but really we never have to worry about
that so we leave that on
i only have one camera on camera one on
but we'll move over
to here and this is our shading position
so this is where how we make the cameras
look pretty
um and again right here i have a control
panel so i can choose what i want i want
to go to camera one right now
i'm gonna do that and
i'm gonna put labels here but we're
still playing with the configuration and
i can see camera one in all of its glory
and then right here is shading so this
is exactly where i'm gonna make
uh make the cameras look how i want them
now
you notice that the number he won here
is red it's actually on air so if we
were streaming we would not
want to edit the camera that's on air we
always try to do the camera that's not
on there
but i can adjust the brightness with
this lever here
um i can use these meters over here to
help me kind of get it where i should
put it up and then i can also change the
db you know if you're familiar with
dslrs or canons or sonys uh this is
basically your iso so we just call it db
in broadcast world because it's actually
the technical term um
and just like iso it comes up in steps
so bring it back down
and zero is the native iso of the camera
we run out about six here
and change colors basically the
objective of this position is really to
make all the cameras look consistent
with each other
we're not always great at that you can
definitely catch that now this is
something that sometimes the director
will do as well
but we always like to have someone who
is dedicated to this position if
possible
um and then we also have comms here so
this is just uh the holy land comm
system
uh this is way less expensive than
clearcom and it's wireless it definitely
has its disadvantage over clear com
but for just doing video it's great we
actually can do up to eight packs
um so eight wireless and then this guy
connects over our cable
to this one and this position and that
position are both wired in
and they have these pretty great
headsets my favorite feature is you flip
this
forward it's unmuted you flip it back
and you're muted
so it's pretty great and you got an ear
open so you can hear the room and that's
all one channel
we're actually adding some equipment
moving some equipment here which is why
it's a mess right here
but um we come over here to our last
position
uh with our social media position so
this is just a mac mini
this one's about seven years old uh and
we use it to run social media so the
commenting
uh the responding to people answering
questions all happens from this position
although we actually haven't been
utilizing it a whole lot for that
it's also great you know there's those
things hey i need to look at the order
service here can i look at the time or
hey i need to print some sheet music
this is a great machine to run to just
to do those things without having to
bother someone else and kind of you know
take that get in their way so this is a
great computer for that
and i have one of the covers off you can
see right here but a big design
requirement for me we need to build this
uh booth was to have cable management
that'd be just to be clean but not just
clean
but also useful doesn't matter that it
looks clean and out of the way if
i want to replace the cable or install a
new part and i have to take everything
apart
so that's where this came in we have
these troughs that are
were built and cool story about this we
actually had
someone in our church who does carpentry
professionally who
gave us a really good price we built all
of this and so he built this you know
these are made out of real wood
and the insane thing about that
is if you look online at broadcast
equipment or
that is built for you know big control
rooms they are ridiculously expensive
you're talking about
a piece of furniture this big across ten
thousand dollars because it has rack
mount stuff
and it has cutouts and all the things
but it's made out of particle board
this is real wood you can see the wood
under here and then we got these
x legs on amazon because it looks pretty
cool and
we built this little five inch box back
here this runs the whole way
and i can show you an area where there's
a little more density of cabling
and it runs to our server room you can
see we bundle things together it's it's
not
beautiful but it's it is serviceable
that's what we care about it has to be
serviceable
um all the sdi comes in here and then
that leads us to
our server room which is right here this
is where the magic happens
you're asking about how we get cables up
here well they all come in through those
pipes we actually installed those pipes
my team did and we bring in all the
green cable you see that's all sdi so
one for each camera
to bring video in and we actually send
one back out
to do camera control so when i'm you
know moving those uh knobs
for on the shading position i'm actually
talking over the to the camera over one
another one of those cables
and the blue is just network there's
security cameras and other network
points in the room
and we installed this ladder and we
actually did hire contractors not a
company but contractors come in just do
the dressing
and pull some of the cable because they
do a great job at it
and then there's that faster that goes
into the server into the into the trough
right there on the other side of the
wall
a little battery for all the battery
backup for all the equipment in the
booth
um and this is everything goes in the
booth that you see right here there's no
other cables that go in there
so uh cable goes over here there's ac in
here
and this is our network rack so this
actually isn't just for
um like i said you know this server room
was built not just for in this room but
really this half the building this is
all of our network um
servers we have a video storage server
batteries at the bottom but what i'm
sure you're interested in is over here
in video land
so the very top is just a dmx splitter
these are sd card recorders
and then oops i did not need to trip on
that cable
um but pro tip
always make sure that you keep cables
free of your server room
we're actually getting to take these out
these are the old cables and so are
these and replace them with the new sdi
we just have to terminate that
but we're gonna try that again so uh in
here
we have our switcher which is right here
so this is the device
that actually is cutting the camera so
when we talk
you know use that box over that panel
there to actually take cameras and pull
the lever
we are doing that um here
so um using this box and then this is
our matrix
i told you all the inputs all the
outputs come into here so all of our
cameras come here first
and they get routed to here and that way
that's how i can from that other
position where i'm shading i can take
that camera
and then mix it in video or shade or
whatever and then from there after the
video is mixed
this is also where it's combined with
audio we'll talk about audio in a minute
it then goes to the encoder now the
stream is as easy as clicking
yeah i got focus lock there
just clicking this on air button and
that sends it right to sub splash
um that's an important piece let me tell
you we were using obs until we got that
guy
and having a stream that getting
streaming is easy
streaming reliably is really hard making
it work every time
this box has been awesome i would say we
do have really good internet here we
have fiber
if you don't look into resi they have a
really awesome protocol that
works even if your internet is a little
flaky if your internet cuts in and out
if our net cuts out even for a second
our stream's down so this works for us
but it may not work for you and your
environment
uh these are just audio consoles for the
band to mix their ears and then
for audio the real meat and potatoes the
magic sauce that we have
is waves and that's what does all of our
so basically a daw for our audio
and it does all of our processing for
our broadcast which ties into our audio
console and our audio room and i will
show you that in a moment
um but i'll show you kind of back here
from a cabling perspective because we
put a lot of attention into that
green is all video blues network orange
is special network
um we really try to keep things clean in
here and
um we have these troughs make them take
it up here to our ladder
uh we have video going all throughout
the building like i said some of these
go to the student room
we actually have a spot for a camera to
plug in and then network
we actually had to add these pipes um i
had this agreement with a volunteer
who thought we should put more piping
here and i was like nah i think we're
fine
and you know i thought this box would be
enough for all of our pipes coming in
and um well we saw who won he was right
we needed more pipe
so we had to add those pipes there um
and
to fit all of our cabling because you
run a lot of cable when you do projects
like this just especially because this
wasn't just
this room it was the entire building
really but we will leave the server room
we're actually going to be putting a
door here
and i said the thing with projects is
the trim work is so hard like we have a
speaker here to get audio in this room
we do have a plan to put more speakers
here but i'll take you into
why is the focus there we go um to take
you into our audio room
so it's kind of a mess in here right now
because we're also using this for
podcasting
but this is our audio room we have an
m32 that's we also have one at front of
house great console
um a display back here for them to see
what's going on hs8 for our speakers
uh to the left we have a mac mini uh
that does recording it runs um
reaper for recording so doll software
somewhere to logic but it ties in really
well to waves
so we use that this desk was custom
built
by matt baker the same guy who did that
desk and we literally set up our
equipment on the ground i took some tape
and taped around it and that was the
outline for the desk and he built it to
spec
uh that guy's just a headphone amp and
these are really helpful meters
you know in the house it's really easy
to know your levels but for broadcast
what's challenging what happens a lot is
people get excited during worship they
crank up the worship in the mix
and then because they don't want to hear
the teaching as loud they turn it down
well the viewer at home needs to be at
the same level consistently
and so we use these to help with that
and you can change that that's a black
magic device as well
over here though is where the true magic
happens and i could spend
hours talking with this about this um
i actually while i helped design this to
actually set this up and and get the
audio tuned in and really figure out
what plugins we had to use
we had an incredible volunteer who is
actually
now leaving in a couple weeks to go to
school to be an audio engineer
really help us figure out our sound and
dial things and figure out what plug-ins
we needed
you know hooking this up is actually
really easy believe it or not it's the
setting it's figuring out you know how
to tune everything figuring out what
plug-ins you're gonna use that's hard
but we use waves for pretty much
everything we use auto-tune
um you know you can see kind of our
stack on
i think these are our vocal channels
yeah vocal channels
so these are stacked on our vocal
channels um these are actually touch
screens but i don't have them plugged in
for touch right now
why is autofocus not there we go
um and we have so there's your two just
del touch screens that tie back into
there
and they connect to the console over
this waves card right here
um and really we're using the console
for levels or using it for
some basic eq uh sometimes some
compression but really everything else
i think we also have some reverb
channels it's happening on waves
and um for the most part our engineers
can come in and just mix and they don't
have to mess with waves too much
um and so we use that and then also we
use this room for
recording podcasts uh c's are just some
seven b's
we have some cloud uh risers over there
our cloud lifters over there
uh this actually used to be just storage
uh so did the server room and
it worked out really well our builders
never planned on having this facility up
here but it just worked out
i'm gonna music off real quick so
actually work where is that coming from
there we go
so let's pull that down um a good note
with broadcast and that's really
important is to use your dcas
um you know in the house if i mute a
channel you really can't tell
but when you're sitting on headphones or
in your car you really can tell
and so rather than mute you know the
instrument just it's tempting for you to
hit the mute groups
you don't want to do that you want to
convert these cas and you want to bring
those down so really program your dc as
well and use those correctly
you can definitely tell when our
engineers who are usually used to mix in
front of house come over here and
use the mute groups that's a big no-no
so
that is pretty much our control room if
you have any more specific
questions definitely feel free to reach
out um
uh shoot me an email a zoom chat maybe
give you a facetime tour
um it's a lot of complexity but like i
kind of said an email
complexity is something that i view is
if it's necessary
i'm all about complexity because it
allows us to do more but with complexity
comes
more training it comes more things that
could fail and for us we had to find
that balance and i think we did
but i always get excited when i can
remove a piece of equipment in fact
we're about to take out our p16s um
because we've been able to move to just
wired and headphones for our
in here so um that's exciting but yeah
that's our broadcast setup if you have
any more questions i'd love to give you
a tour maybe about audio or
if you're in town ever stop by but hope
that helps